I feel like a B7 bomber flying over
enemy territory about to get shellacked
by Flack coming from ground turrets
placed by nutrition ideologues if you
got that reference you might be a
history buff anyway we're about to
travel through divisive Skies as we dive
into a large study that aimed to find
out what happens when you switch out
meat for different plant Foods we'll
cover cardiovascular mortality total
mortality and more so let's get into it
and let's hope that my plane doesn't get
hit although I am partial to the look of
the B25 Mitchell if I had to switch in
this study researchers with really cool
last names I mean check this out kais
Veta orad Maya or Lucas Shing Shak what
are the odds that those are Germans
anyway these researchers pulled 37
observational randomized studies
although the majority were prospective
observations studies and they aim to
find out across hundreds of thousands of
participants what the implications are
for switching out a variety of meats for
plant-based Foods they focused their
analysis on non-patient individuals so
people who were relatively healthy and
they looked at cardiovascular disease
mortality and more included studies had
to meet certain adjustment criteria so
meaning that included studies could not
be you know simple correlations but had
to account for for certain confounding
factors factors that might otherwise
explain the results other than the
substitution of plant foods for meat the
required adjustments include calorie
intake physical activity alcohol
consumption and smoking however I
reviewed the 37 studies and I can tell
you that all of them adjusted for more
than what was required usually including
things like age weight sex menopausal
status history of certain illnesses like
diabetes and heart disease and others so
we come back to this in a bit for now
let's look at the data let's begin by
looking at total cardiovascular disease
which includes cardiovascular mortality
coronary heart disease heart attack
stroke and more see the middle line
above one uh that's the neutral line it
indicates there's no effect of a
substitution if the studies average
together and represented by the blue
diamonds move to the left there's a
benefit of the substitution in reducing
risk now on the far left we see the
substitution analysis for example the
first one says red meat replaced with
and then lists three plant-based Foods
there's more to this interpretation
which we'll get into in just a little
while but for now that's how to read
this so if red meat is replaced by nuts
across four studies including a sample
of 241,000 participants there's a
reduced risk of cardiovascular
consequences the same is true for
replacing red meat with whole grains
however not the case when replacing red
meat with legumes okay before we go on
there's a few considerations here that I
didn't explain before I'm going to be
getting into some statistics and
although I think that it's important for
you to understand if you really hate my
face you're welcome to skip to this Tim
stamp okay for one that I squar or
what's supposed to be an i squared is a
measure of heterogeneity that means that
there's variability in the results of
the studies as in some studies show one
result and others show another the
analysis that we're looking at doesn't
offer that granularity but the
researchers kindly provided a more
detailed view of the results to give us
that information so you'll note a 51%
heterogen for the nuts replacement there
if we pop open the data from the
supplemental data here we see the four
studies on the left side and importantly
the results of the individual studies
note that the study results are not in a
perfect line indicating the same effect
that spread of the results from study to
study is heterogenity meaning that there
isn't a uniform result but that doesn't
mean that the reduction in
cardiovascular disease risk isn't real
okay the second thing that I should
point out is the certainty of evidence
which does not speak to the results
themselves but rather the risk of
potential bias in the studies
researchers are highly encouraged to
report the bias of each study based on
an established a grading system now in
this case the researchers used one
dominant in non-randomized studies
called a Robins assessment now the
researchers acknowledged that with this
type of study that they have used in
this analysis so Association studies
there's always some level of confounding
possible meaning some unaccounted for
Factor influencing the results of the
analysis so they automatically
disqualified every study from being
considered lowrisk of bias meaning there
is some chance the study is biased I
should stress here that it doesn't
actually mean that the studies are are
biased just that there's a chance that's
why if we look at the risk of bias
assessment across all the studies you'll
note this a D1 category which speaks to
confounding it is never indicated green
or low risk of bias on any of these
studies but automatically set to
moderate risk as such the certainty of
evidence is automatically never High and
the highest you'll see is moderate
certainty but don't let that deceive you
because a moderate certainty is defined
as the true effect is close to the
estimated effect meaning we're looking
at an estimated effect based on samples
groups of people that represent the
entire population the true effect is the
effect if we were to measure everyone in
the world or in the population but we'll
never be able to do that so we rely on
samples to give us an estimate of the
true effect as such a moderate certainty
of evidence is actually pretty good
especially if you have a big effect on
the other hand a very low certainty of
evidence means there is a high risk of
bias and we need better data to be
certain of the effect that we're seeing
is accurate now I realize that might
have been a bit much for you and maybe
you're thinking who the f cares but on a
topic where people feel a strong emotion
like plant-based and animal-based
nutrition it's important that I make it
clear what everything means so that we
don't misunderstand I'll have a bit more
to say but let's get back to the results
returning to the cardiovascular disease
we can see that while it is mentioned
that nuts and whole grain in replacement
of red meat did reduce risk the
certainty of evidence indicates many of
these studies are higher in potential
bias and could use more better studies
to shore up the results however that is
not the case when looking at process
Meats in fact the effect is robust and
the certainty of evidence is the highest
that we'll achieve under the parameters
I described earlier other meats like
poultry so chicken turkey Etc also seem
to have elevated risk compared to nut
consumption and again the certainty of
evidence is low so more studies are
needed interestingly fish replacement
with nuts or legumes does not indicate
an effect yet eggs replaced with nuts
does indicate an effect with moderate
certainty of evidence overall these data
indicate the substitution of processed
Meats with just about anything
plant-based as well as the replacement
of egg consumption with legumes have
good evidence behind them reducing
cardiovascular disease risk more data is
likely needed for some of these other
substitutions but some Trend toward
reduced red meat is also currently
indicated in fact we'll also go over
some more specifics like how much of
each which was also addressed in this
analysis first I'd like to get into some
additional work expanding Beyond heart
health and looking at overall mortality
risk for that we can lean on this it
follows similar rules as before but this
time the researchers are able to add a
few more substitutions now as a reminder
the bar for showing an effect on all
cause mortality is higher than that for
cardiovascular disease however in this
case the evidence quality was high
enough and indicates replacing red meat
with nuts does reduce R risk which was
also true when replacing it with whole
grains yet not with cereal or vegetables
although both of these results are based
on fewer studies less certainty of data
and high variability again processed
Meats replaced indicate reduced all
cause mortality risk and again with
large effects interestingly specifically
looking at unprocessed Meats the
replacement with nuts indicates an
effect as well however not the case when
looking at legumes and no no all cause
mortality effect when replacing poultry
with nuts yet good evidence in replacing
eggs with nuts or legumes so these data
indicate that replacing processed meats
and eggs and even red meat in certain
instances with nuts whole grains and
legumes provides a reduced risk of all
cause mortality okay now there's a lot
to say to contextualize what we've just
been over and seeing here including the
amounts of each substitution also I'll
be going over some more more specifics
on the impact that different cooking
oils have on mortality if Dairy follows
similar Trends and the overall impact on
diabetes risk in the extended version of
this video that you're watching if
you're interested in that extended
version and access to all my work my
premium podcast research reviews
summaries and much more uh they're all
part of the physionic Insiders which is
uh Linked In the description for you all
right to contextualize and there's a lot
to contextualize the B7 is hearing
explosions keep her steady open the bay
doors I get a lot of commentary from
people who say that they've switched to
something like a low carbohydrate diet
or a carnivore diet or some other
plantless desert of a diet and I respect
that choice in fact I also acknowledge
that there are randomized control trials
that do show improvements in many health
related metrics like blood sugar insulin
body weight and so on so using what
might be described as not plant-based
analyses like the one that we've been
over are speaking to us in Broad Strokes
they aren't to be taken as an immediate
180 degree turn in one's lifestyle it
would be a bit ridiculous in my mind to
expect a person who's lost I don't know
30 kgrs on a low carbohydrate diet to
Buck their success and switch their diet
entirely based on the word of
researchers especially if they find
certain foods I don't know difficult to
consume or they begin regaining weight
because they don't feel satiated or any
number of reasons however what we can
take away from this kind of work is in
Broad Strokes to choose to add a bit
more nuts into one's diet instead of I
don't know another processed meat for
example slowly making small changes that
Trend toward the results of these kinds
of studies all while keeping
sustainability and your own ability in
the equation is probably a more
reasonable way to go on an individual
level there is more to consider than
cold data but data can inform us on
where to prioritize what we can work on
now in discussion of that data I know
the old adage of correlation is not
causation has already hit my trusty
B17 and no one is saying that
correlation studies should be taken at
face value as immediately indicative of
causation but epidemiology and
biostatistics are not stuck in the 1950s
anymore there are ways of significantly
reducing founding variables again those
are variables or factors that are the
true reason for the results that we've
been over in fact even the researchers
acknowledge that residual confounding as
in remaining factors that could explain
these effects cannot be ruled out but
the researchers do account for many of
the obvious ones and we also have to
consider that if there is a confounding
variable it also has to affect hundreds
of thousands of participants because of
the sheer size of these samples
and it needs to be something reasonable
saying maybe it's x-rays from Mars
specifically affecting meat consumers
needs to have some level of scientific
backing otherwise we never get anything
done and we willy-nilly just throw ideas
out there as if they all have Merit in
short the adage remains but it isn't as
Ironclad as it once was thanks to
statistical progress and huge sums of
data finally before we get into the
amounts of substance institutions the
researchers acknowledge that there's
plenty more data that's necessary to be
certain of some of these results so this
is not an end all analysis by any means
but certain areas have stronger evidence
than others and I'll spell them out for
you next now the substitution amounts
I'm going to add that with the strongest
evidence so we'll cover the main points
as well as the amounts together so
takeway one process meets should be
reduced most analyses indicate consuming
50 g less processed meat and consuming
28 G of nuts reduced cardiovascular
disease risk by over
25% the same reduction in processed
Meats yet an equal 50 g increase in
legumes reduced risk almost by the same
amount finally replacing it with 30 gram
of whole grains reduces Risk by about
35% takeway two red meat should be
reduced most analyses indicated
consuming again 50 g less red meat and
replacing it with 10 to 50 gam of nuts
reduces all cause mortality Risk by
about 7% and replacing it with 11 to 15
gam of whole grains reduces Risk by 4%
takeway three although not a meat which
was the focus here replacing one egg per
day with 25 gr of nuts reduces all cause
mortality Risk by 15% and and 25 to 50 g
of legumes reduces Risk by 10% overall
while there's definitely more data
needed for some of these the trend from
these data indicate at least certain
plant-based foods reduce risk of death
when substituted for unprocess meats and
some evidence also lumps red meat as a
whole into that risk profile now my B17
is still flying so if you want to give
me some more Flack in the comments then
bombs away otherwise
here's a further analysis that I did on
the most potent anti-death food and
here's a hint we discussed it here too